Guide to the Washington Office on Latin America Records, 1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing RL.01401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Geographic Series, 1962-2008 and undated, 250 boxes
  - Guatemala, 1965-2008 and undated, 53 boxes
    - Peace Process, 1982,1988, 1994-2002 and undated (Box 134-146)
      Files document facets of the transition to civil government initiated as a result of accords between the umbrella guerilla group Unidad Revolucionaria Nacional Guatemalteca (URNG) and the Guatemalan government in 1994-1996. These include press clippings about the peace accords as well as copies of them; reports and information related to the United Nations Mission for the Verification of Human Rights and of Compliance with the Comprehensive Agreement on Human Rights in Guatemala (MINUGUA); the Comisión para el Esclarecimiento Histórico (CEH), Guatemala's truth and reconciliation commission; and files related to government efforts to bring the military under civil control. This grouping also includes files related to judicial proceedings stemming from acts committed during the decades of conflict that preceded the peace process as well as instances of witness intimidation by parties wishing to keep cases from coming to trial. Intimidation and abuse of refugees returning to the countryside from Mexico comprise another major strand of human rights cases that became part of the peace process.
    - Politics and Government, 1978-2005 and undated (Box 146-152)
      Specifically concern issues internal to Guatemala. These include elections and campaigns, efforts to reform the administration of justice in Guatemala, and civil policing. Many files document the varying support of political parties for the peace process and political reform. Key issues include the popularity of the Frente Republicano de Guatemala (FRG) and its leaders, former president José Efraín Ríos Montt and Alfonso Antonio Portillo Cabrera. Many files document the Centro de Estudios Estrategicos para la Estabilidad Nacional (ESTNA), which in part facilitated Guatemala's slow transition to civil government.
    - Printed Material, 1977-2008 and undated
      Folders house printed material, much of it in Spanish, created and published by guerilla groups, workers' groups, political parties, and international solidarity organizations, and whose names appear on folder titles. Formats include pamphlets, flyers, newsletters, newspapers, broadsides, announcements, and manifestos. Includes some original communiques and pamphlets created by revolutionary groups in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Among these groups, the Ejército Guerrillero de los Pobres (EGP) and the Organización Revolucionario del Pueblo en Armas (ORPA) are most represented. Both would later become part of URNG. Arranged in alphabetical order by organization name or title of publication. A file of unsorted material appears at the end of the grouping.
      - AFSC [American Friends Service Committee], 1977-1979 (Box 152)
      - Asociación de Estudiantes Universitarios [AEU], 1988-1989 (Box 152)
      - ASIES [Asociación de Investigación y Estudios Sociales], 1996-1997 (Box 152)
      - Barricada!, 1980 July-Aug (Box 152)
      - CECMA [Centro de Estudios de la Cultura Maya], undated (Box 152)
      - Centre for Independence of Judges and Lawyers, 1985 (Box 152)
      - Centro Exterior de Reportes Informativos Sobre Guatemala [Ceri-Gua], 1992-1997, 5 folders (Box 152)
      - Committee of Solidarity with the People of Guatemala (New Hampshire), 1981, undated (Box 153)
      - Comite de Solidaridad con Centroamerica (Toronto), undated (Box 153)
      - Central Nacional Trabajadores [CNT], 1979 (Box 153)
      - Comite Pro Justicia y Paz, 1978-1980 (Box 153)
      - Comite de Unidad Campesina [CUC], 1978-1980, undated, 2 folders (Box 153)
      - Community Action on Latin America [CALA] (Madison, WI), 1980 (Box 153)
      - Commission of Social Justice (San Francisco, CA), 1981 (Box 153)
      - Coordinadora Cristiana de Solidaridad con la Lucha del Pueblo, 1985 (Box 153)
      - Coordinadora Nacional Indigina y Campesina [CONIC], 1994-1995, 2001, undated, 2 folders (Box 153)
      - Coordinadora Nacional de Viudas de Guatemala [CONAVIGUA], 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 153)
      - Defensa Legal Indigena, undated (Box 153)
      - Donde Enmudecen las Conciencias, undated (Box 153)
      - EGP [Ejército Guerrillero de los Pobres], 1981, undated (Box 153)
      - EPICA [Ecumenical Program on Central America and the Caribbean], undated (Box 153)
      - Estudio Diagnostico de la Situación del Arte Indigena en Guatemala, 2008 (Box 153)
      - FDNG [Frente Democratica Nueva Guatemala], 1995-1996 (Box 153)
      - FEDEPAZ [Fundación Ecuménica Para el Desarrollo y la Paz], 2005 (Box 153)
      - Front Line Guatemala, undated (Box 153)
      - Fundación Pro-Guatemala [FUNDAGUA], 1988-1989, undated (Box 153)
      - GAM [Grupo Apoyo Mutuo], 1993-1994 (Box 153)
      - Grupo de Apoyo a Refugiados, 1983 (Box 153)
      - GNIB [Guatemala News and Information Bureau] ¡Guatemala!, 2 folders (Box 154)
      - Guatemala Derechos Humanos Boletín Internacional, 1994-1996 (Box 154)
      - Guatemala Human Rights Update, 1993-1997, 2 folders (Box 154)
      - Guatemala Partners, 1993-1995 (Box 154)
      - Guatemala Scholars Network News, 1992-1995 (Box 154)
      - Guatemala Update (United Kingdom), 1981 (Box 154)
      - IUF [International Union of Food and Allied Workers Associations] Coca Cola plant occupation report, 1983 (Box 154)
      - Maps, undated (Box 154)
      - MICAH [Michigan Interchurch Committee on Central American Human Rights], 1981, undated (Box 154)
      - Momento, 1992, 1993-1997, 2 folders (Box 154)
      - NISGUA [Network in Solidarity with the People of Guatemala], 1985, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 154)
      - Noticias de Guatemala, 1977-1979, 1992, 1994-1996, 4 folders (Box 155)
      - OLAS [Organization of Latin American Students] (University of Chicago), 1981 (Box 155)
      - ORPA [Organización Revolucionario del Pueblo en Armas] publications, 1980-1981, undated, 5 folders (Box 155)
      - PAN [Partido Avanzada Nacional], 1990 (Box 155)
      - PGT [Partido Guatemala del Trabajo], 1981 (Box 155)
      - PAMP [Programa de Acompañamiento al Movimiento Popular], 1993-1994 (Box 155)
      - PAVYH [Programa de Asistencia a Viudas y Huerfanos], 1992 (Box 155)
      - [Maryknoll], 1979 (Box 155)
      - Peace Brigades International, 1994-1996 (Box 155)
      - Radiance, 1982-1983 (Box 155)
      - Reencuentro, 1993-1996, 1 of 2 folders (Box 155)
      - Reencuentro, 1993-1996, 2 of 2 folders (Box 156)
      - REMHI [Proyecto Interdiocesano para la Recuperación de la Memoria Histórica], undated (Box 156)
      - Report on Guatemala, 1987-1989, 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 156)
      - El Retorno, 1993 (Box 156)
      - Reunion, 1994-1995 (Box 156)
      - Solidarity groups/political parties-right wing, 1978-1980, undated (Box 156)
      - Sugar strike, 1988 (Box 156)
      - UASP [Unión de Acción Sindical y Popular] and UNSTRAGUA [Unión Sindical de Trabajadores de Guatemala], 1989 (Box 156)
      - URNG [Unidad Revolucionaria Nacional Guatemalteca] 1986, 1992 (Box 156)
      - WOLA publications, 1988-2004, 8 folders (Box 156)
      - Witness for Peace, 1993-1995 (Box 156)
      - Unsorted serials, 1991-1996, undated (Box 156)
    - U.S. Relations, 1965-1968, 1982-2004 and undated (Box 157-162)
      Covers the extent of the United States' involvement in Guatemala, from direct military and economic aid to numerous and often substantiated claims of clandestine involvement by the CIA in the training and operation of the Guatemalan military. Congressional financial and political support of the Guatemalan peace process as well as files related to diplomatic delegations appear here. The majority of the material chronicles the United States' multifaceted relationship with the Guatemalan military. These include: a few declassified CIA and State Department documents; files on Congressional debates about military and economic aid to Guatemala; and military training at the School of the Americas (SOA), by the CIA, and through the International Military Education and Training (IMET) program.
    - WOLA Files, 1981-2007 and undated (Box 162-173)
      Files document WOLA's activities related to Guatemala, including reports, drafts, and memoranda on the political and human rights situation there, background files, conference materials, and numerous letters to partner organizations in the United States and abroad. Files in this grouping all specifically involve WOLA in some way, either as part of correspondence or as the creator of the files. Because of the diverse nature of WOLA's work, topics covered in this grouping touch all of the other groupings. One audio recording of the WOLA conference The Prospects for Peace in Guatemala completes the series. Additional sound recordings related to Guatemala, possibly including additional cassettes from this conference, may be found in the Sound Recordings Series.
      [Original audio material closed to use. Technical Services may need to have a use copy made before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
  - Guyana,2001
    One folder containing Carter Center report on the 2001 presidential elections.
    - Guyana files (Box 174)
  - Haiti, 1979-2002 and undated, 20 boxes
    Arranged in the following groupings of files: Background Files; Elections; Human Rights; Individuals; Organizations; Police; Politics and Government; Printed Material; U.S. Relations; and WOLA files. Many materials in the Haitian series are in French or Haitian Creole but the majority are in English. Several issues of grassroots publications are found in the sub-series. Unless otherwise noted, subgroupings are unarranged.
    - Background Files, 1979, 1987-2002 and undated (Box 174-175)
      Series of folders on general issues, including the economy, drugs, U.S. relations, and politics and government. One folder includes maps of Haiti.
    - Elections, 1987, 1990s, 14 folders (Box 175)
      Material on Haitian municipal and national elections during the 1990s; includes reports, papers, and other documents, including a copy of the Constitution dated 1987.
    - Human Rights, 1990s (Box 175-177)
      Contains information on human rights abuses, cases, trials, and especially the judiciary (including the Truth Commission). Organizations submitting reports include the Institute for Policy Studies, National Council of Churches, Human Rights Watch, and WOLA. More specific topics include poverty in Haiti, Haitian refugees and U.S. policy toward them; the Haitian military, and the para-military organization FRAPH.
    - Individuals, 1991-2002 (Box 178-179)
      Folders of information representing various individuals linked with Haiti. Includes folders of writings as well as topical folders on politicians, activists, and others. Most are limited to one folder; however, one entire box is devoted to documents on Aristide, including folders on the January 1994 conference in Miami sponsored by Aristide's government concerning political reform and the refugee crisis. Other individuals with folders include Pam Constable, Jonathan Demme, Terry Karl, Rene Préval, Donald Schultz, and Dany Toussaint. Files on individuals are arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Organizations, 1991-2001 and undated (Box 179-183)
      Folders of clippings, correspondence, published reports and other information pertaining to university centers, non-governmental organizations, and other institutions that have addressed Haiti. Substantial materials and prominent organizations include Amnesty International, the Carter Center, Center for International Policy (CIP), Haiti Solidarite Internationale (HSI), Human Rights Watch (Americas Watch), National Coalition for Haitian Rights (NCHR, 2 folders), Organization of American States (OAS, 3 folders), Platform of Haitian Rights Organizations (Haiti: HR Platform, 2 folders), Washington Office on Haiti (WOH, 4 folders). Files on organizations are arranged in alphabetical order (acronyms/abbreviations are often utilized)
    - Police, 1992-2001 and undated (Box 183-186)
      Folders of information including clippings (and photocopies of same), correspondence, notes, reports, and serial publications on a range of issues related to the police and policing activities in Haiti. There are substantial materials on U.N. Reports, Resolutions on Haiti and Security, 1993-2000.
    - Politics and Government, 1993-1996 and undated (Box 186-187)
      Folders of information including clippings (and photocopies of same), correspondence, newsletters, notes, and reports on a wide range of issues related to the Haitian government and politics.
    - Printed Material, 1992-2003 and undated (Box 187-189)
      Organizational information packets, reports, serial publications, study group information circulars, and other materials. Includes one VHS tape of Mickey Mouse Goes to Haiti: Walt Disney and the Science of Exploitation, 1996.
    - U.S. Relations, 1991-1999 and undated (Box 189-191)
      Folders of information including clippings (and photocopies of same), correspondence, notes, reports, press releases, published articles, and serial publications on a range of issues related to U.S. policy towards and relating to Haiti.
    - WOLA files, 1988, 1991-1997 and undated (Box 191-193)
      Folders of general institutional files from WOLA pertaining to Haiti including clippings (and photocopies of same), contact lists, correspondence, notes, reprints of published articles, and other material.
  - Honduras, 1985-2001 and undated, 5.5 boxes
    Files, reports, and clippings, mostly on human rights. Human rights abuses include reports of "disappearances," torture, and killings by the military as well as more general reports on the status of human right in Honduras. The tenor and level of the state's efforts at reform in light of human rights abuses also figure prominently in much of the material. Additional material on Honduran politics and government includes files on elections and the administration of justice by the state. Some earlier files directly and indirectly refer to the Nicaragua-centered Contra War as well as Honduran relations with the United States, including U.S. links to the infamous Battalion 316, which became well-known after a series of newspaper articles in the Baltimore Sun in the mid-1990s. There are also several files on the National Police, responsible for a significant amount of human rights abuses in Honduras. The other files in this subseries are miscellaneous files, some created by WOLA and some photocopies of reports created by Honduran agencies. One videocassette, Zoned for Slavery, an exposé on child labor in Honduran Export Processing Zones appears at the end of the subseries. Files created by WOLA staff, including Paula Church, Jared Kotler, and Bonnie Tenneriello.
    - Honduras files (Box 194-199)
  - Mexico, 1988-2008 and undated, 44 boxes
    Arranged in the following groupings of files: Background Files; Drugs; Economy; Elections; Human Rights; Organizations; Politics and Government; Printed Material; U.S. Relations; and WOLA files. The latter category consists of staff files on trips to Mexico, contact lists, and visit itineraries. The Mexico files chiefly center on political issues, with the largest grouping focusing on Mexican presidential and local elections during the 1990s and later. Other large groupings are for Human Rights - within which exist two boxes of files on events in the Chiapas region during the 1990s - and Organizations, which houses many information files on Mexican human rights organizations and associated movements. Many materials in this subseries are in Spanish. Several issues of grassroots publications can be found in the Printed Material subgroup. Unless otherwise noted, files are in unarranged original order as received. Descriptions of the subgroups follow below.
    - Background Files, 1988-2001 and undated (Box 200)
      Series of folders containing briefings, reports, white papers, and printed material on assorted topics including human rights, drugs, U.S. relations, and politics and government. Significant background material include the State of the Mexican Union address in 1995 by President Zedillo, a white paper from 1991 on NAFTA and human rights, and a set of papers on poverty and social movements in Mexico. One folder includes a photocopy of a map of the Mexican state of Guerrero. Many of these folders also contain related correspondence with exchanges between WOLA and various individuals and organizations.
    - Drugs, 1994-2002 and undated (Box 200-204)
      Folders contain clippings, correspondence, printed material, testimony, and reports on narcotics trafficking, drug control programs and policy, and U.S.-Mexico counternarcotics activities. Background files include a 1992 RAND report on narcotics trafficking in the 1980s, and there are many folders housing U.S. government reports and hearings. Specific topics of interest include the Mexican and U.S. military's role in counternarcotics efforts, as well as narcotics-related corruption in the U.S. and Mexico. Additional material related to drug policy appears in the Drug Policy Subseries of the Initiatives and Activities Series.
    - Economy, 1994-1996, 1997 and undated (Box 205)
      Clippings, correspondence, and printed material pertaining predominantly to Mexico's economic downturn in the mid-1990s, and how this relates to NAFTA, Mexican social movements, and labor rights and other human rights issues.
    - Elections, 1994-2001, 2003, 2004 and undated
      Materials on a broad range of topics pertaining to Mexican national and local civic elections and electoral reform from 1994-2004. The bulk of the material is from the 1994-1997 elections. Formats include articles, elections results, clippings, correspondence, newsletters, opinion polls, reports, Congressional statements, and other printed material. Folders are unarranged within boxes. Other material on elections appear in other subgroupings, in particular Organizations, Human Rights, and Background Files.
      - 1994 Elections, 1994-1995 (Box 205-210)
        Includes folders on organizations such as Alianza Civica (also found in the Organizations Files), Academia Mexicana Derechos Humanos, the Carter Center, and various elections observer groups. The Alianza Civica folders include citizen guides to voting and manuals for poll observers. One set of folders houses extensive publications and documents from the offices of the Mexican Instituto Federal Electoral (IFE), including a full-length report on the 1994 elections. A set of files contains background readings, preparations, and reports from a WOLA delegation trip to Mexico at the end of 1994; the final report from the delegation on the 1994 Mexican elections (Jan. 1995) is included. U.S. Congressional reports and policy materials on pre- and post-election issues are also present. Reports on the Mexican media as related to elections can be found here as well.
      - 1997 Elections, 1996-1998 (Box 210-214)
        Much the same content as the previous elections files above, with an emphasis on electoral reform. Alianza Civica materials are still present, including a large report on the dissemination of information during the elections in all 14 states, as are many reports and publications from the IFE. Box 11 contains a folder of background material on the history of Mexican electoral process and includes a simplified timeline. There are a few files of material on parties such as PRI and PAN, documenting their candidates and stating their position on electoral reform. Includes WOLA's proposal for a grant to send another elections delegation to Mexico for the 1997 election and files and at least one report from the subsequent trip.
      - 2000 Elections, 1999-2000 (Box 215-217)
        Content of folders mirrors material from earlier elections above. Additional printed material comes from the Movimiento Ciudadano por la Democracia and other political reform organizations.
    - Human Rights, 1993-2003
      Material such as clippings, correspondence, and printed material on human rights issues in Mexico, primarily focusing on indigenous rights, peasant uprisings and political action, and workers' rights. Also includes some files on women's issues and gay rights. Split between Chiapas Files and Other Human Rights Files.
      - Chiapas Files, 1993-2002 (Box 217-220)
        Houses documentary material relating to the Zapatista uprisings in the Mexican state of Chiapas and the subsequent violence that erupted, and government repression of indigenous communities. There are many examples and first-hand accounts of human rights abuses. Files also contain reports by various human rights groups, including WOLA, on Chiapas, including individual cases of kidnapping, murder, and other cases that brought international attention to the region; there is a full report on the Acteal massacre in 1997. Other folders pertain to the peace and reconciliation process in the late nineties. See also the WOLA Files subgrouping in box for a folder of information on a 1994 WOLA-sponsored roundtable in the U.S. on Mexico; one session was devoted to the Chiapas peace process.
      - Other Human Rights Files, 1994-2007, bulk 1997-2001 (Box 221-226)
        Files contain information about human rights issues in Mexican states other than Chiapas, although there are items on Chiapas mixed in as they relate to the topic at hand. Materials cover a wide variety of issues: voter rights and other political action issues; indigenous rights; worker's rights (especially for "maquiladoras"); violence against homosexuals, women, and peasants; individual cases of human rights violations, including the Aguas Blancas massacre; and WOLA legislative "Hill drops" on Mexican human rights and other U.S. legislative folders. Individuals named in folder titles include General Gallardo, Digna Ochoa, and environmental activists Rodolfo Montiel and Teodoro Cabrera. Many boxes contain reports from U.S. and Mexican organizations on the human rights situation overall. Files arranged in original order as received.
    - Organizations, 1992-1999 and undated, 16 folders (Box 226)
      Files on organizations, chiefly based in Mexico, typically containing reports, flyers, pamphlets, newsletters, emails, and other documentation. Servicio Internacional Para la Paz (SIPAZ), with its international office in Santa Cruz, California, is the most well-represented with three folders of material, including emails (chiefly exchanges with WOLA staff), minutes of meetings, and newsletters. Other organizations such as Foro Mexicano, Consejo Para la Democracia, Alianza Civica, National Commission for Democracy in Mexico, and Mujeres en Lucha por la Democracia, are represented by smaller amounts of materials.
    - Politics and Government, 1998-2001 and undated, 3 folders (Box 226-227)
      There are relatively few folders in this category, as most of the materials relating to Mexican politics and government are filed within the larger series on elections, narcotics trafficking, and human rights abuses. Material in two folders are focused on specific officials, Carlos Salinas and his criminal trial, and the woman mayor of Mexico City, Rosario Robles. Another folder contains brief information on a SUNY (State University of N.Y.) exchange program with Mexican academics and politicians to reform the Mexican legislature. The remainder of the material covers issues of judicial and security reform.
    - Printed Material, 1994-2008